Ryan Parman

End-to-End Software Engineer: Front-end web engineering, web-tier engineering, API design, distributed systems, micro-services, deployments, management of software lifecycles, and site reliability engineering.

- <u>jobs@ryanparman.com</u>
- (408) 310-7926

Summary

Ryan Parman is experienced at nearly every level of the web stack, from the frontend to the backend, to the systems, servers, and ops. He is an engineer who is fiercely passionate about the user experience and interaction of a product. He inherently understands that the customer is the single most valuable asset an organization can have, and is driven by the unrelenting pursuit of customer-driven focus, ideals and user experience.

Technical Skills and Software

High Proficiency (7-10)

- Operating Systems: macOS, CentOS 6.7 & 7.2
- Standard User Experience Skillset: Human-Computer Interaction Design, Contingency Design
- Standard Front-End Engineering Toolbox: HTML 5, XHTML 1, XML 1, CSS 3, YAML, SVG, DOM, JavaScript, JavaScript Events, JSON, Front-End Performance, jQuery, MVC design pattern, LESS, ESLint, Bootstrap, UglifyJS, progressive enhancement principles, responsive design patterns and more!
- WCAG 2.0 and Section 508 web accessibility guidelines
- HTML5 & CSS 3: Application Cache, Geolocation, History API, Native Video, Selectors, Media Queries, Data Attributes, Building custom Icon Fonts, and more!
- Standard Software Engineering Toolbox: OOP fundamentals, dependency injection, polymorphism, performance, character encodings, Git, Linux, Makefiles, yum, nano, grep, xargs, tee, and other fundamentals, compiling software from source and maintaining in-house RPMs.
- PHP Development Toolbox: Composer, Packagist, PHPT, PHPDocumentor, Monolog, Symfony Framework Components, Slim Framework, Twig, Guzzle, AWS SDK for PHP, cURL, SimpleXML, DOMDocument, iconv, mbstring, APC, Xdebug (cachegrind), SPL, magic methods, PSR recommendations and more!
- Cloud Computing Services: Most of the individual AWS services (not much with the more specialized/newer ones), Google Compute Engine, Google Storage, Google IAM.
- Environments: PHP's Zend Engine, Vagrant, Nginx configuration, PHP-FPM configuration
- Infrastructure & Deployment: Ansible
- Metadata Formats: RSS, Media RSS, Atom, Microformats
- API & Scalable System Design: Understanding and designing highly-scalable, distributed systems for running web applications and web services (e.g., cloud computing). ReSTful web service API design
- Services: Artifactory, JIRA, Confluence, GitHub Enterprise, Phabricator, Toran Proxy, Pingdom, New Relic, Papertrail, GitHub.com

Average Proficiency (4-6)

- Standard User Experience Skillset: Copywriting, Interface Design, Information Architecture, Product Marketing, Community Development
- Standard Software Engineering Toolbox: MacPorts, Homebrew, RubyGems, pip, npm, apt-get, rake, ant, lsof, htop.
- Unit/Integration/Functional Testing: PHPUnit, Selenium, Behat, Mink, PhantomJS, iOS Driver, Travis CI, RubyUnit
- Environments: Python, Ruby, Node.js, HHVM, Docker
- Databases & Key-Value/Document stores: MySQL, Redis
- Metadata Formats: RDFa, Dublin Core, FOAF, CommonTag, OpenSearch, Swagger
- Visual Design Tools: Photoshop, Illustrator, Fireworks, Pixelmator, Acorn
- Services: BitBucket

• Odds-and-ends: Organic search engine optimization, Apache Web Server configuration, Markdown, HTML5 Cross-Origin Resource Sharing (CORS)

Limited Experience, or Interesting Things I'm Starting to Dabble In (1-3)

Persona/user research, Sass/Scss, Haml, DocBook, Memcache, Couchbase, Kafka, Hashicorp tools (Vault, Packer, Atlas, Terraform), Golang, Swift, Node.js, OSSEC, Sensu, rpmbuild.

Work Experience & Notable Projects

Perimeter of Wisdom, LLC

Co-Owner, CTO, and Producer of "The First-Time Offender's Guide to Freedom" (February 2015 - Present)

On the technical side, Ryan built the entire <u>The First-Time Offender's Guide to Freedom</u> website, soup to nuts. Ryan also produced the eBook, authored by E. M. Baird.

Ryan leveraged modern tools to build the front-end, including Bootstrap, LESS, JavaScript, Gulp.js, npm, Bower. Ryan built the back-end in PHP 5.6, using HHVM and Nginx, MySQL, Redis, Slim Framework, Monolog, Pimple, Twig, Guzzle, Doctrine, Phinx, and Symfony components. Ryan deployed the application using Ansible, and developed the application in a Vagrant environment running Ubuntu.

Ryan runs the unit, integration and functional tests using PHPUnit, Behat, Mink, and Selenium. Ryan leverages Amazon SES for sending email, Amazon S3 for static file storage, Stripe for payment processing, Linode for web hosting, MaxMind IP-based geolocation, and Google Books and Dropbox for ensuring that customers always have the latest errata fixes.

WePay — Redwood City, CA

Senior Engineer (April 2014 - Present)

As a member of the API team, Ryan was involved in developing new API endpoints to help expand WePay's business and support its partners. In particular, he was instrumental in developing WePay's MFA-as-a-Service offering (patent pending). Ryan also continues to be heavily involved in the security of WePay's products, coordinating fixes with teams against other priorities, and fixing the issues himself in many cases.

Ryan currently works as a member of the DevOps team, working to improve how WePay provisions cloud infrastructure, deploys updates, manages security patches, monitors applications and infrastructure, and streamlines the process of planning, developing, deploying and maintaining new micro-services throughout the company.

Ryan started and led a year-long, cross-company effort to upgrade the monolithic application's software stack from PHP 5.4 to PHP 5.6. This required cross-team collaboration across all of the major engineering teams, QA, and replacing over 200 servers across multiple environments with zero customer-facing downtime.

Ryan is the owner and maintainer of multiple Tier 1 systems including Artifactory, GitHub Enterprise, Toran Proxy and Phabricator.

Amazon — Seattle, WA

Web Development Engineer II, Amazon Web Services (March 2010 - April 2014)

Ryan is the creator and visionary behind the <u>AWS SDK for PHP</u> — AWS's SDK for rapidly building cloud-based web applications (launched September 2010). He invests heavily in supporting the needs of developers by taking the time to listen and understand the needs of developers, and is involved in PHP-related industry groups on behalf of AWS.

Ryan worked with the <u>AWS Elastic Beanstalk</u> team to provide PHP support for the platform (launched March 2012). In addition to working with the PHP community to determine the configuration for a PHP container that would fit the greatest number of developers, he developed a rigorous internal test suite for testing containers which has been used as the basis for testing by other language-specific teams. He also had early input on adding support for **git push** deployments.

Ryan was heavily involved in the creation and development of the <u>AWS SDK for PHP 2</u>— a best-of-breed SDK (backed by <u>Guzzle</u>— a best-of-breed HTTP framework) that takes into account the numerous changes in the PHP language and community since Tarzan/CloudFusion was first written in 2005 (launched November 2012).

Ryan also works with the AWS Design team on the <u>AWS Management Console</u>, where he lends his experience as a web developer and software engineer to bridge the gap between the design and engineering disciplines in an effort to build a high-quality, robust, user-friendly console for interacting with Amazon Web Services.

(Work experience prior to 2010 can be provided upon request.)

Groups & Accomplishments

- Voting Representative for AWS, PHP Framework Interoperability Group (2012-2013)
- Member, RSS Advisory Board (2007 2009)
- Patent, "Hive-based Peer-to-Peer Network" (WO/2008/033424)
- Patent, "System and Methods for User Authentication across Multiple Domains" (Pending)
- Student guest speaker for the 2004 Silicon Valley College graduation ceremony.

Education

<u>Carrington College California</u> (née Silicon Valley College) — San Jose, CA

- Bachelor of Arts, Design and Visualization, November 2003. 3.84 GPA
- Related Coursework: Web, graphic, multimedia, and publication design.